Guide to the Americas collection, 1811-1920 MS 518
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series IV: United States, 1823-1893; 242356
  - Subseries: Texas (modern boundaries), 1823-1860, 242357
    - Subseries II: 1836-1860. Collection of approximately 75 U.S. Government imprints, consisting of state resolutions for an against the contemplated U.S. annexation of Texas; resolutions of the State of Texas; and documents about Texas. Subjects included annexation, slavery, Santa Fe expedition, 
      - Item 52.29 1845. Tyler, John. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, in reply to a resolution of the Senate of the 19th December, 1844, requesting information in relation to various treaty stipulations between Texas and other independent Powers. 28th Cong., 2d Sess. SD30. [1-7-1845]. Includes correspondence by John C. Calhoun, et al. 11 pp. [Bound with:] additional Printed Documents (SD31-44). Various pagination., 242404 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Item 52.30 1845. [Missouri] Jackson, C.F. Printed Document. Resolutions of the General Assembly of Missouri, in favor of the reannexation of Texas. 28th Cong., 2d Sess. SD46. [1-20-1845]. 2 pp., 242403 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Item 52.31 1845. [New Jersey] McChesney, Charles G. Printed Document. Resolution of the General Assembly of New Jersey, adverse to the annexation of Texas. 28th Cong., 2d Sess. SD78. [2-3-1845]. 1 p., 242402 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.32 1845. [Archer, William S.] Printed Document. Senate of the United States. Mr. Archer, from the Committee on Foreign Relations, submitted the following Report: The Committee on Foreign Relations, to which have been referred sundry joint resolutions and a bill on the subject of the annexation of Texas, and also sundry instructions of State Legislatures… 28th Cong., 2d Sess. SD79 [2-4-1845]. 23 pp., 242401 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.33 1845. Tyler, John. Printed Document. Message of the President of the United States, communicating (in compliance with a resolution of the Senate) information in relation to the official or diplomatic station of Mr. Duff Green near the Government of Texas. 28th Cong., 2d Sess. SD83. [2-7-1845] Includes correspondence by John C. Calhoun. 1 p., 242400 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.34 1845. [Maine] Gerry, Elbridge. Printed Document. Texas and Oregon. Resolutions of the Legislature of Maine, relative to the annexation of Texas and Occupation of Oregon. 28th Cong., 2d Sess. HD112. [Washington:] Blair & Rives. [2-11-1845]. 2 pp., 242399 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.35 1845. [Massachusetts] Bell, Joseph. Printed Document. Report of a Joint Committee and Resolutions of the General Assembly of Massachusetts Adverse to the Annexation of Texas with additional petition by John S. Hanna. 28th Cong., 2d Sess. SD141. [2-27-1845]. 15 pp., 242398 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.36 1845. [Vermont] Merrill, F.F. Printed Document. Resolutions of the Legislature of Vermont against the admission of Texas into the Union without the consent of all the other State of the Union. 29th Cong., 1st Sess. SD25 [12-27-1845]. 1 p., 242397 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.37 1846.[Medill, W.] Printed Document. Documents in Relation to the Difficulties existing in the Cherokee nation of Indians. 29th Cong., 1st Sess. SD301. [Washington:] Ritchie & Heiss. [4-20-1846]. 9 pp., 242396 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.38 1846. Polk, James K. Printed Document. Message of the President of the United States, communicating information of the existing relations between the United States and Mexico, and recommending the adopting of measures for repelling the invasion committed by the Mexican forces upon the territory of the United States, with additional documents. 29th Cong., 1st Sess. SD337. [Washington:] Ritchie & Heiss. [5-11-1846]. Includes correspondence by John Slidell, James Buchanan, et al. 131 pp., 242395 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Item 52.39 1846. Polk, James K. Printed Document. Occupation of Mexican Territory. Message from the President of the United States, in answer to a resolution of the House of Representatives of the 15th instant, relative to the occupation of the Mexican Territory, with 19 additional documents. 29th Cong., 2d Sess. HED19. [Washington:] Ritchie & Heiss. [12-22-1846]. Includes correspondence by Zachary Taylor, et al. 109 pp., 242394 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Item 52.40 1846.[New Hampshire] Hale, John P. Printed Document. Annexation of Texas. Resolution of the Legislature of New Hampshire, relative to the annexation of Texas, and the encroachment of the slave power. 29th Cong., 2d Sess. HD23. [12-29-1846] 2 pp., 242393 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Item 52.41 1847.Polk, James K. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, to the two houses of Congress, at the commencement of the first session of the thirtieth congress, with additional documents. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SED1 Washington: Wendell and Van Benthuysen, 1847. 44 pp., 242392 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Item 52.43 1848. Marcy, W.L. Printed Document. Report of the Secretary of War, showing the number of troops in the service of the United States in Mexico since the commencement of the war, the killed and wounded, &c. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SED36. [4-10-1848]. 86 pp., 242391 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Item 52.44 1848. [Texas] Henderson, James W. Printed Document. Resolution of the Legislature of Texas, in favor of the establishment of a line of military posts between Red river and the Rio Grande, and the adoption of measures for preserving the friendly relations between the Indian tribes and the people of that State. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SMD122. [Washington:] Tippin & Streeper. [4-17-1848]. 1 p., 242390 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Item 52.45 1848. Polk, James K. Printed Document. House of Representatives. Correspondence between the Secretary of War and General Scott. Message of the President of the United States, transmitting the correspondence between the Secretary of War and Major General Scott, with the accompanying documents, in compliance with the resolution of the House of Representatives of the 17th instant. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. HED59. [4-26-1848] 63 pp., 242389 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Item 52.46 1848. Polk. James K. Printed Document. Message of the President of the United States, with communications from the government of Yucatan, representing the state of suffering to which that country is reduced by an insurrection of the Indians, imploring the protection of the United States, and offering, in case it should be granted, to transfer the dominion and sovereignty of the peninsula to the United States. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SED40. [4-29-1848]. Includes correspondence by James Buchanan. 19 pp., 242388 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Item 52.47 1848. [Texas] Henderson, James W. Printed Document. "Proviso," Slavery, the Tariff, and the War with Mexico. Resolutions of the legislature of Texas, in relation to the proviso, slavery, the tariff, and the war with Mexico. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. HMD91. [Washington:] Tippin & Streeter. [5-18-1848] 2 pp., 242387 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Item 52.48 1848. Medill, W. Printed Document. In the Senate of the United States. Communication from the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, and other documents, in relation to the Indians of Texas. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SRCD171. [6-15-1848]. 52 pp., 242386 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Item 52.49 1848. Polk, James K. Printed Document. House of Representatives. Treaty with Mexico. Message of the President of the United States, transmitting a copy of the treaty of peace, friendship, limits, and settlement, between the United States and the Republic of Mexico, ratifications of which were exchanged at the city of Queretaro, in Mexico, on the 30th of May, 1848. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. HED69. [7-22-1848] 74 pp., 242385 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Item 52.50 1848. Polk, James K. Printed Document. Message of the President of the United States, in answer to a resolution of the Senate, calling for the proceedings of the court of inquiry convened at Saltillo, Mexico, January 12, 1848, for the purpose of obtaining full information relative to an alleged mutiny at Buena Vista, about the 15th August, 1847. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SED62. [7-12-1848]. 213 pp., 242384 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Item 52.51 1848. Polk, James K. Printed Document. House of Representatives. New Mexico and California. Message of the President of the United States, transmitting in answer to resolutions of the House of Representatives of July 10, 1848, reports from the Secretaries of State, Treasury, War, and Navy. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. HED70. [7-24-1848]. Includes correspondence by James Buchanan, John Y. Mason, Robert Stockton, et al. 49 pp., 242383 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Item 52.52 1848. Polk, James K. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, communicating, in compliance with a resoultion of the Senate, the proceedings of the two courts of inquiry in the case of Major General Pillow. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. SED65. [8-2-1848]. 633 pp., 242382 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Item 52.53 1850.Crawford, George W. Printed Document. Military Forces Employed in the Mexican War. Letter from the Secretary of War, transmitting information in answer to a resolution of the House, of July 31, 1848, relative to the military forces employed in the late war with Mexico. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. HED24. [1-24-1850]. 34 pp. + 9 folding tables., 242381 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Item 52.54 1850. [Osborne, William S.] Printed Document. William Osborne. Mr. Finis E. McLean, from the Committee of Claims, made the following Report: The Committee of Claims, to whom was referred the memorial of William S. Osborne… 31st Cong., 1st Sess. HR24. [1-29-1850]. 1 p., 242380 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Item 52.55 1850. [New York] Bogart, William Henry. Printed Document. Resolutions of the Legislature of New York, For the abolition of the slave trade in the District of Columbia; against an extension of slavery or the jurisdiction of Texas over any part of New Mexico; for the admission of California, and in favor of the preservation of the Union. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD52. [2-21-1850]. 2 pp., 242379 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Item 52.56 1850.[Sanchez, Enrique]. Printed Document. Memorial of Enrique Sanchez and others, citizens and residents of the territory and valley of the Rio Grande. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD61. [2-28-1850]. 3 pp., 242378 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Item 52.57 1850. [Smith, Hugh N.] Printed Document. Hugh N. Smith, Delegate from New Mexico… The Committee of Elections, to which were referred the credentials and the memorial of Hugh N. Smith, esq., praying to be admitted to a seat in the House, as a delegate from New Mexico, respectfully submit the following report. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. HR220. [4-4-1850]. 4pp., 242377 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Item 52.58 1850. [Texas] Keenan, C.G. Printed Document. Resolutions of the Legislature of Texas, relative to the payment of certain volunteer companies for services on the western frontier of that State. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD100. [4-17-1850]. 1 p., 242376 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Item 52.59 1850. [Texas] Keenan, C.G. Printed Document. Resolution of the Legislature of Texas, in favor of an appropriation for a light-house or light-boat at Brazos Santiago and the mouth of the Rio Grande. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD100. [4-17-1850]. 1 p., 242375 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Item 52.60 1850. [Texas] Keenan, C.G. Printed Document. Resolution of the Legislature of Texas, in favor of an arrangement between the United States and Mexico for the mutual surrender of criminals, robbers, persons held in bondage, or fugitives from justice. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD 101. [4-17-1850]. 1 p., 242374 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Item 52.61 1850. [Texas] Keenan, C.G. Printed Document. Resolutions of the Legislature of Texas, on the subject of the United States district court in that State. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD102. [4-17-1850]. 1 p., 242373 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Item 52.62 1850. [Texas] Keenan, C.G. Printed Document. Resolution of the Legislature of Texas, in favor of the granting of pensions to persons who suffered in the Texas revolution. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD103. [4-17-1850]. 2 pp., 242372 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Item 52.63 1850. [Texas] Keenan, C.G. Printed Document. Resolution of the Legislature of Texas, relative to the extension of the jurisdiction of that State over the Red River. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD104. [4-17-1850]. 1 p., 242371 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Item 52.64 1850. [Texas] Webb, James. Printed Document. Resolutions of the Legislature of Texas on the subject of slavery. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD106. [4-23-1850]. 2 pp., 242370 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Item 52.65 1850. Taylor, Zachary. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, in answer to a resolution of the Senate calling for information in relation to the formation of a State government in New Mexico. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SED60. [7-1-1850] 2 pp., 242369 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Item 52.66 1850. Fillmore, Millard. Printed Document. (Part II) Message from the President of the United States, in answer to a resolution of the Senate calling for information respecting the organization of a State government in the Territory of New Mexico. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SED60. [7-18-1850]. 3 pp., 242368 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Item 52.67 1850. Fillmore, Millard. Printed Document. Texas Boundary. Message from the President of the United States, in reference to the Texas Boundary. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. HED82. [8-6-1850]. Includes correspondence by Daniel Webster. 12 pp., 242367 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Item 52.68 1850. Fillmore, Millard. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, relative to the claim of Texas to jurisdiction over part of New Mexico. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SED67. [8-6-1850]. Includes correspondence by Daniel Webster. 12 pp. [Bound with:] Fillmore, Millard. Message from the President of the United States, Explanatory of his message relative to the claim of Texas to jurisdiction over part of New Mexico. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SED67. [8-8-1850]. 1 p., 242366 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Item 52.69 1850. Fillmore, Millard. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, Explanatory of his message relative to the claim of Texas to jurisdiction over part of New Mexico. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. WSED67. [8-8-1850] 1 p., 242365 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Item 52.70 1850. Fillmore, Millard. Printed Document. Message from the President of the United States, explanatory of that part of his late message in reference to New Mexico and Texas which alludes to the receipt of Governor Bell's letter. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. HED85. [8-28-1850]. 1 p., 242364 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Item 52.71 1850. Fillmore, Millard. Printed Document. Texas Boundary. Message from the President of the United States, announcing to Congress the agreement by Texas to the propositions of boundary offered by a late act of Congress. 31st Cong., 1st Sess. SMD72. [12-16-1850]. 9 pp., 242363 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Item 52.72 1852. [Corwin, Thomas]. Printed Document. Memorial of a Committee appointed at a meeting of the Creditors of Texas. 32nd Cong., 1st Sess. SMD72. [4-20-1852]. 9 pp., 242362 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Item 52.73 1856. [Marcy, William L.]. Printed Document. Claim of James B. Watson. Letter from the Secretary of State, in reference to the claim of Mr. Walton, as a messenger to the government of Texas. 34th Cong., 1st Sess. HED121. [7-20-1856]. 2 pp., 242361 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Item 52.74 1860. [Butt, Geroge N.]. Printed Document. George N. Butt, Survivor of Butt & Black. The Court of Claims submitted the following report. 36th Cong., 1st Sess. HRCCD213. [2-11-1860]. 39 pp., 242360 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Item 52.75 1850. Buchanan, James. Printed Document. Difficulties on Southwestern Frontier. Message from the President of the United States, communicating, in compliance with a resolution of the House, information in reference to the difficulties on the southwestern frontier. 36th Cong., 1st Sess. HED52. [4-2-1860]. Includes correspondence by John B. Floyd, et al. 147 pp., 242359 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series V: Cuba, 1896; 242354
  - 06-16-1896. Grajales, Antonio M. Letter: Liberation Army instructions for dealing with members of the enemy camp given " the fact that the political situation has changed in our favor."Cites Gen. Weyler; proclaims "Country and Freedom". In Spanish. 2 pp., 242355 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Spain, 1812; 242352
  - [1812] Printed document. [Spain] Constitucion politica de la monarquia española. Promulgada en cadiz a 19. de Marzo de 1812. Cadiz: Imprenta Real. Early edition of the Spanish Constitution, with preliminary matter not found in other copies: an engraved title page, 8 preliminary leaves containing a decree of march 1812, authorizing printing of the Constitution, a decree of 2 May 1812 ordering that the promulgation of the new Constitution be celebrated throughout Spanish dominions, and a decree of 24 May 1812 regarding how the clergy and the populace should celebrate the Constitution. The eighth leaf is a printed title for the Constitution. 134 pp., 242353 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series VII: Portugal, 1822; 242350
  - [1822] Printed document. [Portugal] Constituição politica da Monarchia Portugueza. Lisbon: Na Imprensa Nacional. First edition of first Portuguese Constitution. 100 pp., 242351 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Multi-country, 1811-1914; 242325
  Scope and Contents note
  Subject relates to two or more countries, or is written by one country about another.
  - 1811, [Whipple, Oliver] Nine Letters, Particularly Addressed To The People Of The Revolting Spanish Provinces Of The Caraccas, And To Other Spanish Provinces In North And South America: And To The Whole Spanish Nation And The Civilized World. By Don Augosto Revilo Elppihw, Artium Magister. Anglecised And Correctly Compared With The Spanish. Written July, 1810. Baltimore. A scarce pamphlet arguing the against the independence movements in Latin America. 27pp. (Pm, #26), 242349 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 9-30-1830. Signed document. Bustamante, Anastasio. Shortly after Mexico has warded off an attempted Spanish reconquest. Events "called me to the position of Vice President and charged me with Executive Power... the relationship that must exist between the United States of Mexico and your Republic [Bolivia] becomes interwoven as is convenient to our mutual interests." Also signed by the Secretary of Foreign Relations, Lucas Alaman y Escalada. To [Andres de Santa Cruz y Calahumana]. 2 pp. (#60), 242348 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1830. Harrison, William Henry. Remarks of General Harrison, late Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the United States To The Republic of Colombia, On Certain Charges Made Against Him By That Government. Washington, D.C. 69pp. Harrison's signature is cropped. (SB, #7), 242347 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 12-12-1835. Cramp, James. [Letter: Texas Revolution, Mexico, Filibustering] Remarkable letter written two days before his execution at Tampico. Cramp had been swept up in the Tampico Expedition of exiled Mexican military officer Jose Antonio Mexia. (incomplete) (ALS, #15.01), 242346 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 12-1835. Cramp, James. Letter, manuscript fair copy, in Cramp's hand, of the Declaration and Petition of the American prisoners who were subsequently executed at Tampico. (incomplete) (AL, #15.02), 242345 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1835. Newsclippings, statements, lock of hair, related to executions at Tampico. (collateral to #15), 242344 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - [2-8-1837] Jackson, Andrew. Claims Upon Mexico. Message from the President of the United States, Upon the Subject of the Claims of the United States Upon the United Mexican States. 24th Cong., 2d Sess. HED139. American Claims against Mexico resulting from the Mexican seizures of American persons and property, after Texas Independence. 105 pp. (Pm, #47), 242343 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - [1840-1842] Key, Francis Scott. Interpreting the Convention's provisions to assure prompt payment of the claims of his clients, avoid "unnecessary and injurious delay," and to exact Mexico's payment of interest. 4pp. (Pm, #53.01), 242342 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 6-14-1842. Tyler, John. Message from the President of the United States, Communicating… Information Touching the Proceedings Under the Convention of the 11th April, 1839, Between the United States and the Mexican Republic. 27th Cong., 2d Sess. SD320. 255pp. plus 12 folding tables. (Pm, 53.02), 242341 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1846. Newman, John B. Texas and Mexico in 1846; Comprising the History of Both Countries, With an Account of the Soil, Climate, and Productions of Each. Scholarly examination of the settlements in Texas, the competing land claims, and the climate and agriculture of Texas and Mexico, in which he criticizes the annexation of Texas. 32pp. (Pm, #51), 242340 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1848. [Mexican War: Polk] Messages of the President... On the Subject of the Mexican War. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. HED60. "A compilation of all correspondence ... relating to the Mexican war." 1277 pp., [bound with] Correspondence Between the Secretary of War and Generals Scott and Taylor, and Between General Scott and Mr. Trist. 30th Cong., 1st Sess. HED56. Provides numerous detailed reports on the war, the conflicts among the generals and the government, and the status of peace negotiations. 405 pp., ix. (Bound volume, cataloged separately.), 242339 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - [1-1-1848] [Mexican War: Polk] The Mexican War. Review of the Annual Message of the President of the United States to Congress, December 7, 1847. A Whig attack on Polk refuting his argument for the Mexican-American War. 32 pp. (Pm, #49), 242338 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 4-7-1848. Letter: Byrd, Lieut. R.K. The arrival of the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. Molino del Rey, Mexico. With integral address leaf; cancel mark stamped "Vera Cruz Mexico April 12." Small quarto. To Major William McEwin. [3] pp. (ALS, #21), 242337 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 4-27-1848. [Florida-Mexican War] Florida Whig – extra. Eucheeanna Convention. The Delegates Having Convened… Marianna, [Fl.]. The Whig Party of West Florida condemning the Mexican War. (Br, #20), 242336 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 5-7-1848. [Mexican American War] M. Mattock letter. Mexico "is the most broken country that my eyes ever beheld… Some say that peace will be made and others say it will not so it is a difficult matter for one to come to a definite conclusion…" To Major W. S. McEwen. 3pp. (ALS, #58), 242335 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - [3-2-1849] Polk, James K. [Brazil: Slavery] Correspondence Between the Consuls of the United States at Rio de Janiero, with the Secretary of State, on the Subject of the African Slave Trade. 30th Cong., 2d Sess. HED61. Documenting the illegal slave trade between Africa and Brazil, and involvement of American ships and slave-traders. 223pp. (Pm, #55), 242334 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - [6-24-1853] Fillmore, Millard. Correspondence in Relation to Central America. 32d Cong. 2d Sess. SED27. Colonial Claims from ministers of Central American countries, protesting British colonial claims to Nicaragua and Honduras. 106 pp. (B, #46), 242333 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 10-22-1857. Buchanan, James. Treaty Between the United States and Peru. Washington. Folio. Countersigned by Lewis Cass as Secretary of State. 199pp. (MDS, #31), 242332 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - [1860] [Sumner, Charles] Confidential. Convention with the Republic of Venezuela, For the Adjustment of Claims of Citizens of the United States… [Washington]. Senator Charles Sumner's copy, with his name (but not signature) at the head of the first page. 4 pp. (PD, #19), 242331 (Box 5, Folder 14)